A nobody
名もなき小者
Not worth mentioning
取るに足らぬ
I'll remember your face
貴様の顔覚えたぞ
Retreat
撤退せよ
Brothers
仲間らよ
Pursue with all our might
徹底的に追撃せよ
Leave none alive
一人も逃すな
Wait
待て
Chen Ying
陳応
You still want to stop us?
陳応よ
I've already given you all my military merit
まだ阻むか
Completely
我が軍功はすべてお前に譲りしものを
You dare go back on your word
約束を破る気か
General Zu
祖将軍
I only promised to hold Yiyang
我が約束は弋陽の守りのみ
Pursuing the Wuzhao is too risky
追撃は危険すぎる
All soldiers
諸将士よ
The Wuzhao trampled the central plains
鄔奴は馬で中原を踏みにじり
Oppressed our people
同胞を虐げた
If we let the Wuzhao return north
もし鄔奴を北へ帰すならば
Next time those who suffer
鄔奴軍の北帰を放置せば
May be your families
次に泣きを見るはお前らの家族
And friends
友かもしれぬ
Sons of Xuan
宣国の漢たちよ
How can we endure such humiliation?
如何にこの辱を耐え得ん
Northern volunteers
北地の義士らは
Still dare to fight to the death
なお死を恐れず戦っている
Those with courage
度胸のある者は
Follow me and kill
我に続け
Without my order
我が命を待たぬ者
No one moves
誰一人動くことを許さぬ
Kill
討て
The sun sets
太陽が沈み
Liu Dadao, at some point
劉大刀はいつの間にか
Was pierced by a spear
一本の長槍に貫かれ
Kneeling backward in the sunset
夕焼けの中で天を仰いで跪いていた
On both sides of him
彼の両脇を
Xuan's iron cavalry thundered past
宣国の鉄騎が駆け抜けてゆく
He gazed at the pink sky
彼は薄紅色の空を見つめ
Finally released the blade in his hand
ついに手の中の大刀を放した
Facing death
死が目前にあらば
Who isn't afraid?
誰が恐れぬであろうか
Who isn't a coward?
誰が臆病者でないであろうか
But there are always some beliefs
されどある信念こそが
That can support
臆病者の背骨を
A coward's backbone
支えることができるのだ
Liu
劉
Liu Nian
劉念
I, Sikong Yao, swear
俺司空耀が誓う
I will protect her
必ず彼女を守り
Warm clothes and full bellies
暖かい衣と十分な食事を与え
Peace and happiness
平安と喜びある暮らしをさせると
General Liu
劉将軍
You and the brothers
仲間らよ
Rest assured
ご安心を
The imperial physicians said
侍医たちも申していた
Not to get too emotional
侍医が申すには
Your head condition
あまり感情を高ぶらせず
Needs rest
頭の病は安静が肝要と
Those physicians
侍医など何を知る
Know nothing
か道士どもが告
The Daoist masters said
げるは三災九難
Three disasters, nine hardships, ten trials
十劫を越えし後に
Must pass through to achieve immortality
こそ長寿を得んと
Born
生まれた
How is it?
どうだ
Congratulations, Your Majesty
陛下
Congratulations, Empress
皇后さま
It's a son
お慶び申し上げます 男の子にて候
Good
よい
I will richly reward the Xie family
朕は謝氏に厚く褒美を与える
Let's go
行くぞ
I want to see my grandson
朕は孫を見に行く
Look at him
見よこの子を
He's smiling, he's smiling
笑っておるぞ 笑っておる
His eyes
この目は父
Are like his father's
に似たり
His nose
鼻は朕に似
Takes after me
ているんだ
This is the eldest grandson
これは長孫なり
Your Majesty should give him a name
名を賜らねばなりませぬ
Good
よし
Sheng
盛
Call him
司空盛
Sikong Sheng
とせよ
Father is wise
父上の御英明盛
Sheng
とは北地大勝北と南
Is for the great victory in the north
を結ぶ運河がまもなく
Is for the north-south canal
貫通して運を開かんと
Soon to be opened for prosperity
する盛まことに
Is from heaven
蒼天我が大宣を護り国
Blessing Great Xuan's flourishing fortune
運が盛んであることを示す盛
We
我ら
Have a good daughter-in-law
良き嫁を得たり
Sheng'er
盛よ